Guide to the Gustaf Sobin Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gustaf Sobin papers
1952-2005
YCAL MSS 647
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
48
(48 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence and writings that document the life and work of the American poet Gustaf Sobin. Correspondence sheds light on his relationships with other literary figures, including René Char, James Laughlin, Hyatt Waggoner, and Charles Tomlinson, among others. Writings consist of extensive notes and drafts for most of his major works and provide comprehensive documentation of his creative process.
Sobin, Gustaf, 1935-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Susannah Sobin on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Gustaf Sobin (1935-2005)
Gustaf Sobin was an American poet who made his home in Provence, France, for more than three decades. His body of work includes poetry, prose, and fiction, almost all of it reflecting his deep connection to the Provençal landscape.
Sobin was born November 15, 1935, in Boston, Massachusetts, and was educated at Brown University (A.B., 1958). His published books of poetry include: Wind Chrysalid's Rattle (1980), Voyaging Portraits (1988), and Towards the Blanched Alphabet (1998), among others. His published works of prose and fiction include: Dark Mirrors: A Novel of Provence (1992) and Luminous Debris: Reflecting on Vestige in Provence (1999), among others.
Sobin died of pancreatic cancer, July 7, 2005, in Cavaillon, Vaucluse, France.
"Gustaf Sobin." Contemporary Authors Online. Detroit: Gale, 2005. Gale Biography In Context. Web. 2 Nov. 2012.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence and writings that document the life and work of the American poet Gustaf Sobin. Correspondence sheds light on his relationships with other literary figures, including René Char, James Laughlin, Hyatt Waggoner, and Charles Tomlinson, among others. Writings consist of extensive notes and drafts for most of his major works and provide comprehensive documentation of his creative process.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1952-2005. II. Writings, 1955-2005.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Provence (France); Authors -- 20th Century; Poets -- 20th Century; Char, René, 1907-1988; Laughlin, James, 1914-1997; Sobin, Gustaf, 1935-; Tomlinson, Charles, 1927-2015; Waggoner, Hyatt Howe, 1913-1988
- Correspondence, 1952-2005; Series I; 11; (11 boxes)
  - Academie Des Sciences, Agriculture Arts Et Belles Lettres, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Alliance Française, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Almino, Joao, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Ambo Anthos, 2000-2002 (Box 1)
  - Ashbery, John, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Bahti, Tim, 2002-2004 (Box 1)
  - Baker, Robert, 1996-2002; 2 (Box 1)
  - Berger, John, 1974-1987 (Box 1)
  - Berlin Verlag, 1999-2004; 2 (Box 1)
  - Bershtel, Sara, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Bishop, Judith, 2002-2004 (Box 1)
  - Bloomsbury Publishing Ltd, 1991-2001; 4 (Box 1)
  - Brito, Manuel, 1992-2000 (Box 1)
  - Brown, Clarence, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Chapman, Lee, 2000-2003 (Box 2)
  - Char, René, 1962-1969, 1986; 4 (Box 2)
  - Cheng, Francois, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Chile Poesia, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Cleaver, Diane, 1990-1993 (Box 2)
  - Clifford, James, 1973-2004; 9 (Box 2)
  - Cole, Peter, 1997-2000 (Box 2)
  - Contemporary Authors, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Creeley, Robert, 1988-2004 (Box 2)
  - Davidson, Michael, 1988-2002 (Box 2)
  - Deguy, Michel, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Deming, Alison H., 1995 (Box 2)
  - Denver Quarterly, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Donahue, Joseph, 1990-2002 (Box 2)
  - Doris, Stacy, 1990-1996; 2 (Box 3)
  - Drew, Elizabeth, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Duncan, Robert, undated (Box 3)
  - Duplessis, Rachel, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Editions De L'Aube, 1999-2002 (Box 3)
  - Enslin, Theodore, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Eshleman, Clayton, 1978-2004; 4 (Box 3)
  - Featherston, Dan, 1996-2001; 2 (Box 3)
  - Fedier, François, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Felstiner, John, 1996-2004; 2 (Box 3)
  - Fete Du Livre, 1986, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Film Projects (includes Loncrane, Richard; Rissient, Pierre; Craddock, Malcolm; Langdon, Mayra; Lucchesi, Sandra; Robbins, Richard), 1991-2003; 2 (Box 3)
  - Fondation Saint-John Perse, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Foss, Phillip, 1987-1995 (Box 3)
  - Foster, Ed, 1990-2004; 7 (Box 4)
  - Fourcade, Dominique, 1965-2004 (Box 4)
  - Fowlie, Wallace, 1964 (Box 4)
  - France Culture, 2000 (Box 4)
  - Frazer, Tony, 1980-2002; 8 (Box 4)
  - Galassi, Jonathan, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Gallup, Donald, 1952-1953 (Box 5)
  - Gander, Forrest, 2001 (Box 5)
  - Gladding, Jody, 1998-2003 (Box 5)
  - Greilsamer, Laurent, 2000-2001 (Box 5)
  - Griffin, Jonathan, 1980-1985 (Box 5)
  - Grinell, E. Tracy, 2003-2004 (Box 5)
  - Hale, Terrel D., 1990 (Box 5)
  - Hart, Kevin, 2002 (Box 5)
  - Hemingway, Ernest (includes correspondence with Hemingway associations), 1952-1957, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Hemingway, Ernest (includes one letter to Sobin, a typed copy of a letter letter to Gustaf Sobin's brother, H. Sobin from Hemingway, and photocopies of signed inscriptions by Hemingway to Sobin.), 1961 (Box 5)
  - Hickman, Leland, 1983-1990 (Box 5)
  - Hilbert, Ernie, 2001 (Box 5)
  - Hinton, David, 1993-2004 (Box 5)
  - Hirsch, Edward, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Hitchcock, George, 1976-1978 (Box 5)
  - Hocquard, Emmanuel, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - Hollander, Benjamin, 1987-1992 (Box 5)
  - Hoover, Paul, 1992-2003 (Box 5)
  - Howe, Fanny, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Howe, Susan, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - Hrechdakian, Sabine, 1997-2004; 7 (Box 5)
  - Ignatieff, Michael, 1974-2005; 3 (Box 5)
  - Indyk, Ivor, 1997-2004; 5 (Box 5)
  - Internationales Literaturfestival, Berlin, 2002 (Box 5)
  - Irby, Ken, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Irwin, Mark, 1986, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Jolas, Tina, 1966-1997 (Box 5)
  - Joris, Pierre, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Joron, Andrew, 1999-2004 (Box 5)
  - Kasper, Catherine, 1997-2004 (Box 6)
  - Kelly, Robert, 1997-1999 (Box 6)
  - Laughlin, James (includes others), 1974-1997; 4 (Box 6)
  - Lehman, David, 1990-2001 (Box 6)
  - Levi Strauss, David, 1987-1988 (Box 6)
  - Little, Brown and Co., 1990-1992; 2 (Box 6)
  - Lopez Mills, Teddy (includes interview), 1990-2001; 4 (Box 6)
  - Mackey, Nathaniel, 1984-2004 (Box 6)
  - MacLow, Jackson, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Magnaghi, Ambrogio, 1965-1991; 2 (Box 6)
  - Magnaghi, Marco, 2001-2004; 2 (Box 6)
  - Martenson, Jennifer, 1996-2001 (Box 7)
  - McClure, Michael, 1985-2003 (Box 7)
  - Messerli, Douglas, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Michaux, Henri, 1983-1984 (Box 7)
  - Miller, Jeffrey, 1983-1999; 15 (Box 7)
  - Mobilio, Albert, 1987-1998; 2 (Box 8)
  - Morrow, Bradford, 1982-1984, 1997-2004; 7 (Box 8)
  - Nakell, Martin, 1996-1997 (Box 8)
  - Needell-Hollander, Claire, 1995-1998 (Box 8)
  - New Directions Publishing Corp., 1983-2001; 5 (Box 8)
  - Niedermeiser, Andrew, 1999-2004; 3 (Box 8)
  - W.W. Norton and Co., 1998-2002; 5 (Box 9)
  - O'Brien, Geoffrey, 1987-2002 (Box 9)
  - O'Brien, Michael, 1988-2004; 7 (Box 9)
  - Oppen, George, 1980 January 6 (Box 9)
  - Palmer, Michael, 1981-2005 (Box 9)
  - Perloff, Marjorie, 1995 (Box 9)
  - Peyre, Henri, 1966 (Box 9)
  - Phillips, Denis, 1985-1986 (Box 9)
  - Pound, Ezra, 1956 May 25-26 (Box 9)
  - Prevallet, Kristin, 1994-2001 (Box 9)
  - Ramke, Bin, 1996, 2003 (Box 9)
  - Rasula, Jed, 1996, 1997 (Box 9)
  - Riemen, Rob, 1999-2001 (Box 9)
  - Riggs, Sarah, 2002-2003 (Box 9)
  - Robinson, Elizabeth, 2000-2004 (Box 9)
  - Rodney, Janet, 2004 (Box 9)
  - Ronk, Martha, 1996 (Box 10)
  - Rothenberg, Jerome, 1991-2003 (Box 10)
  - Royet-Journoud, Claude, 1986-1988 (Box 10)
  - Rudman, Mark, 1981 (Box 10)
  - Sarterelli, Stephen, 1994-2002 (Box 10)
  - Schwabsky, Barry, 2003-2004 (Box 10)
  - Schwartz, Leonard, 1996-2002 (Box 10)
  - Sieburth, Richard, 1979 January 9 (Box 10)
  - Sonnenberg, Kerri, 2000 February 7 (Box 10)
  - Spahr, Juliana, 1999-2000 (Box 10)
  - Taggart, John, 1967 February 28 (Box 10)
  - Tejada, Roberto, 1986-1996 (Box 10)
  - Tomlinson, Charles, 1975-1995; 3 (Box 10)
  - Turnbull, Gael, 1983-1994; 3 (Box 10)
  - University of California Press, Berkeley, 1997-2001; 6 (Box 10)
  - Van Doren, Mark, 1955 June 19 (Box 10)
  - Waggoner, Hyatt, 1957-1980 (Box 10)
  - Walter, Eugene, 1958, 1961 (Box 10)
  - Weinberger, Eliot, 1977-1999; 13 (Box 11)
  - Weiss, Allen S., 2000-2005; 2 (Box 11)
  - Welish, Marjorie, 1996 January 11 (Box 11)
  - Who's Who in America, 1998-1999 (Box 11)
  - Yip, Wai-Lim, 2003 (Box 11)
  - Zawacki, Andrew, 1999-2004 (Box 11)
- Writings, 1955-2005; Series II; 37; (37 boxes)
  - Early work 1955-1962
    - "Femina and Other Poems," typescripts, 1955-1960 (Box 12)
    - Poems, typescripts, 1960-1962; 2 (Box 12)
    - "Telegrams," drafts, final typescript, published work, 1960-1963; 3 (Box 12)
    - Poetry, typescripts and drafts, 1962-1972; 5 (Box 12)
  - Wind Chrysalid's Rattle (1980)
    - First fragments, 1973 (Box 13)
    - First drafts, pocket notebooks, 1973-1974; 2 (Box 13)
    - Drafts, 1974-1975; 7 (Box 13)
    - Binder, 1975; 2 (Box 13)
    - Worksheets, 1975 (Box 13)
    - Autograph manuscripts, drafts, undated (Box 13)
    - First complete draft, undated (Box 13)
    - Typescripts, 1975-1979; 8 (Box 14)
    - Publication preparation material, 1979 (Box 14)
    - Uncorrected typescript, undated (Box 14)
    - Typescript carbon copy, undated (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous, 1973-1975 (Box 14)
    - French Translation, 1975 (Box 14)
    - Corrected copy, 1975 (Box 14)
  - Celebration of the Sound Through (1982)
    - "Nomadic Iris," "Portrait," "Voice," "Ode for Charles Tomlinson," "Ash," "Wetness," "Caesurae: Ways Without," drafts, 1976 (Box 14)
    - Binder, 1976 (Box 14)
    - Part 1, binder, 1976-1977 (Box 15)
    - First half, draft, 1977 (Box 15)
    - Second half, draft, 1977 (Box 15)
    - "Nomadic Iris," sequence, 1977 (Box 15)
    - Autograph manuscript, draft, 1978; 2 (Box 15)
    - "Enamel Violet," "Sounds in Shadow and Substance," "Troubadour," "The Poem," drafts, 1979-1980 (Box 15)
    - "Voluttes," "Lagoon: Reliquia," "Violets," drafts, 1979-1980 (Box 15)
    - "Violets," "Mardolins," "Shadow Rattles III," drafts, 1979-1980 (Box 15)
    - "Li Shang-Yin," draft, 1979 (Box 15)
    - "Tang," "The Cheval Glass," drafts, 1979 (Box 15)
    - "Troubador," "Shadow Ratttles," "Persona," "Altar," "Cerisiers," "Flowering Cherries," "Leis Espaventaus," drafts, 1979; 2 (Box 15)
    - Incomplete work, drafts, 1978-1979 (Box 15)
    - "The Cherval Glass," "Caesurae: Midsummer," "Drafts: For Santa Cruz," "Seven Masks for an Eclipse," drafts, 1979 (Box 15)
    - Copies of completed work, undated (Box 16)
    - Preparation for publication, 1981 (Box 16)
    - Part I, "Waves' Scaffolds," typescript, 1977 (Box 16)
    - Part II, "Nenuphar," typescript, 1980 (Box 16)
    - Complete typescript prior to publication, 1981 (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous poems, 1979-1980; 2 (Box 16)
  - The Earth As Air (1984)
    - "Carnets," draft, notes, 1979-1982; 2 (Box 16)
    - Rejected material from "Carnets", 1979-1982 (Box 16)
    - "Madrigal," draft, 1980 October (Box 16)
    - "And Thus Unto," draft, 1981 (Box 16)
    - "And Thus Unto," exercise book, 1981 (Box 16)
    - "The Cardplayers," draft, 1980-1981 (Box 16)
    - Notes, 1980-1981 (Box 16)
    - Early drafts, 1981 November (Box 16)
    - Drafts, 1981; 3 (Box 16)
    - Completed draft, final typescript, 1981 September (Box 16)
    - "Breathherd," draft, 1981 (Box 17)
    - "Flowering Almonds," "Outside and In," draft, 1981 (Box 17)
    - "Irises," draft, 1981 (Box 17)
    - "Eleven Quatrains and a note from Ventadour," draft, 1981 (Box 17)
    - "Girandole," draft, 1981 (Box 17)
    - "Ray," draft, 1982 (Box 17)
    - "As It Unravels," draft, 1982 October (Box 17)
    - "Manna," draft, 1982-1983 (Box 17)
    - "Cirque: or Upward Gathered Out," draft, 1983 (Box 17)
    - "Las Alpilles," draft, 1983 (Box 17)
    - Worksheets, Completed-Uncompleted work, 1980 (Box 17)
    - Rejected material, notes, 1980-1982; 4 (Box 17)
    - Drafts, fragments, 1982 (Box 17)
    - "Nulla Undulata: Notes on Rhythm," rejected draft, 1982 (Box 17)
    - "The Earth as Air," first complete typescript, undated (Box 17)
    - "The Earth as Air," final state, undated (Box 17)
    - Final typescripts, carbon copies, notes, undated; 2 (Box 18)
  - Sicilian Miniatures (1986)
    - Draft, typescript, 1983; 2 (Box 18)
  - Ideograms in China (2002)
    - Drafts, typescript, undated; 2 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Drafts
    - Completed, unpublished work, 1970 (Box 18)
    - Fragments, typed extracts from notebooks, drafts, 1982-1987; 2 (Box 18)
    - Checklist for publication, 1976-1984 (Box 18)
    - "On the Dogon," draft, notes, 1980 (Box 18)
    - "Children's Tale in Prose," draft, 1979 (Box 18)
    - Poetry notes, fragments, 1974-1982; 2 (Box 18)
    - Pocket Notebooks, one literary address book, 1973-1985; 5 (Box 18)
  - Voyaging Portraits: Poems (1988)
    - Miscellaneous rejected material, 1983-1986; 2 (Box 19)
    - Exercise books, 1983-1986; 2 (Box 19)
    - "Nile," "July the Night," "Along the Lines the Lines Move," "Neither Wind nor Anemones," drafts, 1983 (Box 19)
    - "Transparent Itineraries: 1983," draft (Box 19)
    - "Only the Milkiest Emulsions," draft, 1984 (Box 19)
    - Fragments, Rejected Work, 1983 (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous Works, 1983-1984; 2 (Box 19)
    - "Transparent Itineraries: 1984-1985," draft (Box 19)
    - "Eleven Rock Poems," draft, 1984 (Box 19)
    - Fragments, Rejected Work, 1984-1985 (Box 19)
    - "Januarius," draft, 1985 (Box 19)
    - "Violet City: Aspects of the Transitive," draft, 1985 (Box 19)
    - "Out of the Identical," "A Fable for Lighea," "Two Paths," drafts, 1985 (Box 19)
    - Fragments, Rejected Works, 1985 (Box 19)
    - "A Portrait of the Self as Instrument of Its Syllabus," draft, 1984; 4 (Box 19)
    - "Road, Roadsides and the Disparate Frames of Sequence," preliminary notes, working drafts, 1986; 4 (Box 20)
    - "Ferrara Unleavened," draft, 1986 (Box 20)
    - "Rome Poems - Fragments," draft, 1986 (Box 20)
    - "Of Our Floral Sign and Ascendant," draft, 1986 (Box 20)
    - "Seven Excerpts from a Flora of Speech," draft, 1987 (Box 20)
    - "Voyaging Segments: A Frieze," draft, 1987; 2 (Box 20)
    - "Lineage," draft, 1987 March (Box 20)
    - Title deliberations, 1987 (Box 20)
    - "Voyaging Portraits," early typescript, 1983-1987 (Box 20)
    - "Voyaging Portraits," final typescript, undated (Box 20)
  - Articles of Light and Elation (1998)
    - First drafts, 1988-1989; 5 (Box 20)
    - First drafts, 1988-1989; 2 (Box 21)
    - Drafts to final typescript, 1988-1989; 5 (Box 21)
  - Venus Blue (1991)
    - Early work: notes, outlines, research and preparatory materials, 1987; 3 (Box 21)
    - Notes on central characters, undated (Box 21)
    - Research material on Los Angeles and 1930s Cinema, undated (Box 21)
    - Research material on Aviation and 1930s Fashion, undated (Box 21)
    - Research material, undated (Box 21)
    - Early rejected work, 1987 (Box 21)
    - 2 Early versions of Chapter 1, undated (Box 21)
    - Chapter 1, draft, undated (Box 22)
    - Chapter 2, draft, undated (Box 22)
    - Chapter 3, draft, undated (Box 22)
    - Chapter 4, draft, undated (Box 22)
    - Chapter 5, draft, undated (Box 22)
    - Chapter 6, draft, undated (Box 22)
    - Chapter 7, draft, undated (Box 22)
    - Chapter 8, draft, undated (Box 22)
    - Chapter 9, draft, undated (Box 22)
    - Chapter 10, draft, undated (Box 22)
    - Chapter 11, draft, undated (Box 22)
    - Completed draft, 1989; 2 (Box 22)
    - Corrections, 1989-1990; 2 (Box 22)
    - Pre-Publication material, 1990 (Box 22)
    - "Venus Blue, an Iconography," album, 1990 (Box 22)
      Scope and Contents
      A 22 page picture album of character and set locations evoked in novel.
    - Photocopy of draft with corrections, undated; 2 (Box 23)
    - Uncorrected proofs, 1990; 2 (Box 23)
    - Final typescript, 1990; 3 (Box 23)
    - Proofsheets, 1991; 2 (Box 23)
    - Corrected photocopies, 1991; 2 (Box 23)
  - Dark Mirrors: a Novel of Provence (1992)
    - Chapter 1, draft, undated (Box 23)
    - Chapter 2, draft, undated (Box 23)
    - Chapter 3, draft, undated (Box 23)
    - Chapter 4, draft, undated (Box 23)
    - Chapter 5, draft, undated (Box 23)
    - Chapter 6, draft, undated (Box 23)
    - Chapter 7, draft, undated (Box 23)
    - Chapter 8, draft, undated (Box 23)
    - Chapter 9, draft, undated (Box 24)
    - Chapter 10, draft, undated (Box 24)
    - Chapter 11 & 12, draft, undated (Box 24)
    - Chapter 13 & 14, draft, undated (Box 24)
    - Preparatory Notes, undated (Box 24)
    - Page 1-50, completed draft, undated (Box 24)
    - Page 51-100, completed draft, undated (Box 24)
    - Page 101-130, completed draft, undated (Box 24)
    - Page 131-155, completed draft, undated (Box 24)
    - Page 156-188, completed draft, undated (Box 24)
    - Rewrite, 1st 41 pages, undated (Box 24)
    - Rewrite, 1st 73 pages, undated (Box 24)
    - Version 2, typescript, undated; 3 (Box 24)
    - Version 3, typescript, undated; 3 (Box 24)
    - Version 4, typescript, undated; 2 (Box 25)
    - Version 4, corrected, final typescript, undated; 3 (Box 25)
    - Bloomsbury page proofs, undated (Box 25)
    - Rewrites, 1991; 5 (Box 25)
    - "Raised Game," typescript, 1991; 2 (Box 25)
  - "Worshipped Woman"
    - Notes, draft, completed versions, undated; 3 (Box 25)
  - "The Secret History of Secrets," short stories
    - Drafts and corrections, undated; 4 (Box 25)
    - "Pauline and Forever After," draft, typescript, undated; 5 (Box 26)
    - "Gwen Tuttle and her Husband," drafts, undated; 3 (Box 26)
    - "That Lightest of Elements," drafts, undated; 3 (Box 26)
    - "From Canary to Chartreuse," drafts, undated; 3 (Box 26)
    - "A World of Myrrh," drafts, undated; 5 (Box 26)
    - "La Consolata," drafts, undated; 3 (Box 27)
    - "The Gardens of the Marches," drafts, undated; 4 (Box 27)
    - "The Call," drafts, undated; 2 (Box 27)
    - "A Blue Befitting," drafts, undated; 3 (Box 27)
  - "A Heaven Gone Under"
    - Preliminary notes, outlines, drafts, 1993; 20 (Box 28)
    - Early typescript, draft, completed version, graphic material, circa 1993; 8 (Box 29)
  - Breaths' Burials: Poems (1995)
    - Index, acknowledgements, undated (Box 29)
    - "As If Written in a Book of Glass," draft, undated (Box 29)
    - "Ode to the Elaboration of Interval," draft, undated (Box 29)
    - "Fourteen Irises for J. L.," "Gothic," drafts, undated (Box 29)
    - "Transparent Itineraries: 1991," draft (Box 29)
    - "Psalmodic," "Anguish-Metaphor," "Tracing a Thirst," drafts, undated (Box 29)
    - "The Villas of Andrea Palladio," draft, undated (Box 29)
    - "On the Nature of the Iconic," "The Genius of Release," drafts, undated (Box 29)
    - "Idiom," "Dawn, and the Ground," "The Death of Flash Back," drafts, undated (Box 29)
    - "Lines from Pietro Longhi," draft, undated; 2 (Box 29)
    - Part 3: "Preface," "A Portrait without Features," "Entry," "Densities of Naught," "Lamp," "Transcript," drafts, undated (Box 29)
    - Part 3: "Teatro," "Domino," "Absolution," "Transparent Itineraries: 1992," drafts (Box 29)
    - Part 3: "Article of Faith," "Breath's Burials," "Eckhart," "Poesis: A Conceit," "Portrait of Sorts in Mid-March," drafts, undated (Box 29)
    - "Saint Veran," "The Gaze," "An Afterlife," "Was Where We Go," drafts, undated (Box 30)
    - "Transparent Itineraries: 1993," draft (Box 30)
    - "Odes of the Extravagated I-III," draft, undated (Box 30)
    - "Odes of the Extravagated IV-V," draft, undated (Box 30)
    - "Odes of the Extravagated VI-VII," draft, undated (Box 30)
    - "Breath's Burials," completed typescript, undated (Box 30)
    - Further final corrections, typescript, undated (Box 30)
    - Final working draft with corrections, 1993 October 14 (Box 30)
    - Final corrections prior to publication, undated (Box 30)
    - Photocopied proofsheets, undated (Box 30)
    - Graphic material for color illustration, undated (Box 30)
      Includes contact prints and negatives
  - Miscellanea, Rejected Material, Four Line Poems
    - "Left to the Body Alone," draft, undated (Box 30)
    - Rejected material, draft, 1991-1993; 2 (Box 30)
    - "Object of all Labor," Four Line Poem, draft, 1993 (Box 30)
    - "Chaplade," "Breathshots: Four-line Exercises in Verse," Four Line Poem, drafts, undated (Box 30)
    - "Winter," and Untitled Four Line Poems, drafts, undated (Box 30)
    - Four Line Poems, draft, undated; 2 (Box 30)
    - Pocket Notebooks, 1990-1999; 8 (Box 31)
    - French Translations, 1990-1999; 2 (Box 31)
    - Rene Char & Paul Eluard French Translations, undated; 2 (Box 31)
  - Luminous Debris: Reflecting on Vestige in Provence and Languedoc (1999)
    - Drafts, 1995; 4 (Box 31)
    - "Neolithicizing Provence," draft, undated (Box 32)
    - "Archaeological Rhetoric," draft, undated (Box 32)
    - "Moon Goddess," draft, 1995 (Box 32)
    - "The Skull with the Seashell," draft, undated (Box 32)
    - "West Southwest," draft, 1995 (Box 32)
    - "A Twilight Industry," draft, undated (Box 32)
    - "Stellae: the Emergence of Human Figuration," draft, 1995 (Box 32)
    - "On a Bronze Age Earring," draft, undated (Box 32)
    - "Echoes in Clay," draft, undated (Box 32)
    - "Baby Burials: Domestic Inhumation in the Iron Age," draft, undated (Box 32)
    - "Terramare," draft, undated; 2 (Box 32)
    - "On the Longevity of Typonyms," draft, undated; 2 (Box 32)
    - "The Cult of Skulls: from Severance to Sculpture," draft, undated (Box 32)
    - "Negative Architecture," draft, undated (Box 33)
    - "Undulant-Oblique," draft, undated (Box 33)
    - "Tracking Hannibal," draft, undated (Box 33)
    - "What the thunder said," draft, undated (Box 33)
    - "Aeria the Evanesant," draft, undated (Box 33)
    - "Votive Mirrors," draft, undated (Box 33)
    - "Dream Incubation: the Temple at Riez," draft, undated (Box 33)
    - "Fervor and Residue," draft, undated (Box 33)
    - "Le Pont Flavien," draft, undated (Box 33)
    - "Aquaductus I," draft, undated (Box 33)
    - "Aquaductus II," draft, undated (Box 33)
    - "Aquaductus III," draft, undated (Box 33)
    - Original typescript, undated (Box 33)
    - Proofsheets, undated; 2 (Box 33)
    - Proofsheets from Marsilio, UC Press, 1997; 4 (Box 34)
    - Publicity Abstract, 1998; 2 (Box 34)
    - 2nd and Final Proofsheets, 1999 (Box 34)
  - By the Bias of Sound: selected poems 1974-1994 (1995)
    - Corrections, Pre-Publication notes, 1994 (Box 35)
    - Proofsheet Sets 1-3, undated; 3 (Box 35)
  - The Fly Truffler: a novel (1999)
    - Notes, undated (Box 35)
    - Preliminary draft, undated (Box 35)
    - Corrected photocopies of working draft, undated (Box 35)
    - First working draft, undated (Box 35)
    - Photocopy of draft, undated (Box 35)
    - First complete draft, undated (Box 35)
    - Typescripts, undated; 5 (Box 35)
    - Version A, complete & bound, undated (Box 36)
    - Deleted pages, checklist, undated (Box 36)
    - Drafts, typed inserts, 1998 (Box 36)
    - Version B, bound, undated (Box 36)
    - Version B, photocopies with comments, 1998 (Box 36)
    - Final corrections, rewrites, 1999 (Box 36)
    - Pages replaced, 1999 (Box 36)
    - Final Version B, Version C, 1999 (Box 36)
    - Version C with minor corrections, 1999 (Box 36)
    - "Foul Material," etc..., undated; 2 (Box 36)
    - Second pass masterset, 1999 (Box 36)
    - Interview drafts, undated (Box 36)
    - Bloomsbury page proofs, undated (Box 36)
    - French translation, undated (Box 36)
  - Towards the Blanched Alphabets (1998)
    - Part 1: "The Empty Alphabets," "Genesis," "Under the Bright Orchards," drafts, 1996 (Box 37)
    - Part 1: "Fugues," "Pastorale," "Premices," drafts, 1995 (Box 37)